RESUME

Dr. G.Nataraj
Assistant Professor (Sr.)
School of Mechanical Engineering
Vellore Institute of Technology, Vellore, Tamil Nadunataraj.g@vit.ac.in
8754375303

SUMMARY

I am working as a Senior Assistant Professor in the school of mechanical engineering, VIT University Vellore for the past 2 years. My research specialization is in the field of internal combustion engines, more specifically in Low-temperature combustion technology like premixed charge compression ignition (PCCI), homogeneous charge compression ignition (HCCI), and reactivity controlled compression ignition (RCCI) engines.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. - Mechanical Engineering

Anna University, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 01/2019

Master of Engineering – Thermal Engineering

Anna University, Tiruchirappalli, Tamil Nadu

04/2015

Bachelor of Engineering – Mechanical Engineering

V.S.B Engineering College, Karur, Tamil Nadu 05/2013

EXPERIENCE

Assistant Professor (Sr.)
School of mechanical engineering
VIT University Vellore, Tamil Nadu

05/2019 to till date

RESEARCH EXPERTISE

- > Thermal Engineering
- > Internal Combustion engines
- ➤ Alternative fuels (Biodiesel, Methanol, Biogas, Hydrogen, and CNG)
- > Energy from waste
- > Nano technology

PAPER PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Ganesan, N.,** Masimalai, S., Ekambaram, P., & Selvaraju, K. Experimental Assessment of Effects of n-Butanol on Performance, Emission, and Combustion Characteristics of Mahua Oil Fueled Reactivity Controlled Compression Ignition (RCCI) Engine.
- 2. Pradeep Raju, Senthil Kumar Masimalai, **Nataraj Ganesan**. "Extracting methyl-ester from waste cooking oil for fueling a light duty diesel engine a dual fuel approach." Energy Sources, Part A: Recovery, Utilization, and Environmental Effects (2020): 4-10.
- 3. Raju, Pradeep, Senthil Kumar Masimalai, **Nataraj Ganesan**, and S. V. Karthic. "Engine's behavior on hydrogen addition of waste cooking oil fueled light duty diesel engine-A dual fuel approach." Energy 194 (2020): 116844.
- 4. Kumar, AR Mahesh, M. Kannan, and **G. Nataraj**. "A study on performance, emission and combustion characteristics of diesel engine powered by nano-emulsion of waste orange peel oil biodiesel." Renewable Energy 146 (2020): 1781-1795.
- 5. Karthic, S. V., M. Senthil Kumar, **G. Nataraj**, and P. Pradeep. "An assessment on injection pressure and timing to reduce emissions on diesel engine powered by novel biodiesel." Journal of Cleaner Production (2020): 120186.
- 6. Karthic, S. V., M. Senthil Kumar, **G. Nataraj**, and P. Pradeep. "Experimental investigations on the influence of hydrogen and LPG mixtures on performance behavior of a mahua bio oil-powered dual fuel engine." International Journal of Green Energy 16, no. 12 (2019): 878-889.
- 7. **Ganesan, Nataraj**, and Senthilkumar Masimalai. "Experimental investigation on a performance and emission characteristics of single cylinder diesel engine powered by waste orange peel oil biodiesel blended with antioxidant additive." Energy Sources, Part A: Recovery, Utilization, and Environmental Effects (2019): 1-12.
- 8. Masimalai, Senthil Kumar, **Nataraj Ganesan**, S. Pasupathiraju, and T. Mohanraj. Investigations on the Combined Effect of Oxygen Enrichment and Water Injection Techniques on Engine's Performance, Emission and Combustion of a Mahua Oil Based Compression Ignition Engine. No. 2018-01-0929. SAE Technical Paper, 2018.
- 9. Kumar, M. Senthil, **G. Nataraj**, and S. Arul Selvan. "A comprehensive assessment on the effect of high octane fuels induction on engine's combustion behaviour of a Mahua oil based dual fuel engine." Fuel 199 (2017): 176-184.

10. Masimalai, Senthilkumar, Jai Kumar Mayakrishnan, and **Nataraj Ganesan.** A Comprehensive Assessment on Combined Effect of Thermal Barrier Coating and Emulsification Techniques on Engine Behavior of a Mahua Oil Based Diesel Engine. No. 2017-01-0873. SAE Technical Paper, 2017.

TEACHING EXPERTISE

- ➤ Heat Transfer
- > Automotive engines
- > Emission control and techniques
- > Thermal engineering systems

Yours truly, G.NATARAJ